Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf officially מ"ג. Mem Gimmel.
We're in מ"ב עמוד ב'. Mem Bais Amud Beis. We pick up
about five lines from the top. אחת בתולות ואחת בעולות. Achas besulos
v'achas beulos. Talking about the three months wait before a woman gets
remarried to determine whether whether she's pregnant
and the משנה Mishna says whether she is a virgin or a
non-virgin, whether it was her first marriage was אירוסין Eirusin or נישואין,
Nissuin, even though in those cases logically we know that she's not
pregnant. Nevertheless, it's a type of לא פלוג Lo plug but then
we hear that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
both disagree and say that if the first marriage was only an
אירוסין Eirusin or if the second one is then there's no need
to wait or if it was a נישואין Nissuin but right now
she's only undergoing אירוסין Eirusin there's also no need to wait. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says:
היינו בתולות והיינו ארוסות. Hayinu besulos v'hayinu arusos. Why did it say
two things: virgins and only having having been ארוסה? Arusa? It's the
same thing. היינו בעולות והיינו נשואות. Hayinu beulos v'hayinu nisuos. Seeing a
non-virgin is the same as being a נשואות. Nisuos. We should, so
why is it distinguishing that? The גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבי יהודה,
Amar Rabbi Yehuda, הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what it means:
אחת בתולות ואחת בעולות Achas besulos v'achas beulos שנתאלמנו או שנתגרשו she'nisalmu
o she'nisgarshu בין מן האירוסין בין מן הנישואין. bein min haeirusin bein
min hanissuin.
How do you get those two cases? Women who were either divorced
or widowed from אירוסין Eirusin and נישואין, Nissuin, meaning so אירוסין Eirusin
and נישואין Nissuin it's just an explanation of the first two categories,
it's not really a different category. All right. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
לא אתא lo asa לבי מדרשא. l'bei medrasha. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
didn't come to the בית מדרש. Beis medrash. אשכחיה Ashkchei
לרבי אסי. l'Rabbi Assi.
אמר ליה Amar lei מאי אמור רבנן בבי מדרשא? mai amur rabanan
b'bei medrasha?
What did the rabbis say in the בית מדרש? Beis medrash? So
רבי אסי Rabbi Assi said, if you want to know you should
have been there. No. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him,
הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה
כרבי יוסי. halacha k'Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, we rule
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says that we don't say לא
פלוג. Lo plug. רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, both רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say that it would only be a
problem if the women were originally in נשואה Nissua and they were
now going doing a נישואין, Nissuin, so there was a possibility of
sex before and sex now. But if it was an ארוסה Arusa
at either end, it would not be a problem. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi made another point about her being an אבילה Aveila which we'll
get to. But anyway, we rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So
the גמרא Gemara says, now remember רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan normally goes
like a סתם משנה. Stam mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says: מכלל
דיחידאה פליגי עליה? Mikhlal d'yechida pligi alei?
Does that suggest that the סתם Stam who argues on רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi and says לא פלוג Lo plug and you always need
a three months wait, that that סתם Stam is really a דעת
יחיד, Daas yachid, it is not a consensus or not a majority
but only a single opinion? אין, In, yes. דתניא, De-tanya, and I'll
show it to you. We see in a ברייתא. Brayisa. הרי שהיתה
רדופה לילך לבית אביה. Ha-rei she-hayta redufa le-veich ve-aviha. So now we're
going to have a whole series of cases where we can assume
that the woman is not pregnant and we're going to still say
that you need a three months wait. Okay, the type of לא
פלוג Lo plug of our משנה. Mishna. הרי שהיתה רדופה לילך לבית
אביה. Ha-rei she-hayta redufa le-veich ve-aviha.
This woman was always running after to be in her father's house,
meaning that during the period leading up to her husband's death, she
had been in her father's house. It's a funny phrase רדופה, Redufa,
but anyway, she had not been with her husband for a long
period of time. או שהיה לה קטטה עם בעלה, O she-haya la
katas im ba'ala, or she and her husband were having a fight
and I don't know, somehow we could have an assumption that they
weren't having sex during that time. Again, some of these are very
funny because you know, it's one thing to say okay אירוסין Eirusin
or whatever, something very formal and and sort of measurable. These types
of things leave it to be very vague in terms of determining
who falls into that category. I mean, would it just all be
just an issue of self-reporting? Maybe it would be. Anyway, או שהיה
בעלה חבוש בבית האסורין, o she-haya ba'ala chavush b'veis ha'asurin,
or the husband was in jail. או שהיה בעלה זקן, O she-haya
ba'ala zakein, or he was elderly, so much so that he could
not, I mean even if they had sex, we could assume that
he was not able to have children through,
oh we'll get to that. או חולה, O choleh,
or he was sick so couldn't be having sex. או שהיתה היא
חולה, O she-hayta hi chola, or she was sick. או שהפילה אחר
מיתת בעלה, O she-hipila achar misas ba'ala, or she had a miscarriage
after her husband's death, so obviously she's not pregnant. או שהיתה עקרה,
O she-hayta akara, or she was a infertile. או זקינה, O zkeina,
or elderly, post-menopausal. או קטנה, O ktana, or too young. או אילונית,
O ailonis, or she was a woman who was born never able
to have children. או שאינה ראויה לילד, O she-eina reu'ya l'leid, or
any reason she couldn't have kids. In all these cases doesn't matter,
צריכה להמתין ג' חדשים tzricha l'hamtin gimmel chodashim דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir.
She has to wait three months. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. So anyway, the point of all that is, there is an
idea of לא פלוג Lo plug out there, but it's a דעת
יחיד, Daas yachid, it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה מתיר ליארס
ולהינשא מיד Rabbi Yehuda matir l'areis v'linasei miyad
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or some have the גירסא Girsa רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi because both of them make it
make this distinction between when when it can be determined or not
determined, they allow her to do אירוסין Eirusin right away, meaning even
if she had even if well, it's funny, it says ליארס ולהינשא
מיד, l'areis v'linasei miyad, right. So even a woman who was נשואה,
Nissua, she could have אירוסין Eirusin right away and in these cases
she could even do נישואין Nissuin right away. Okay, so you see
that it is a מחלוקת Machlokes of דעת יחיד Daas yachid and
therefore רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was able to פסקן Pasken like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda slash רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that makes it that
it's not a problem if she for her to marry immediately for
even נישואין Nissuin if it was a situation in which she could
not be have be pregnant.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי חייא בר אבא Amar Reb
Chiya bar Abba חזר בו רבי יוחנן. Chazar Bo Reb Yochanan.
רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan reversed himself and now he's going back to
say לא פלוג lo plug that we always need three months wait.
So חזר בו רבי יוחנן. Chazar Bo Reb Yochanan. אמר רב יוסף
Amar Rav Yosef אי הדר ביה, i hadar bei,
if he reversed himself, ממשנתא דכרמא הדר ביה. mi-misneisa d'karma hadar bei.
He reversed himself because of the ברייתא Braisa that of the- of
the vineyard, meaning of כרם ביבנה. Kerem B'Yavne. דתניא De'tanya we learned
in a ברייתא, Braisa, אמר רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא Amar Reb Yishmael b'no shel Reb Yochanan ben Broka שמעתי מפי
חכמים בכרם ביבנה, shamati mipi chachamim b'Kerem B'Yavne,
I heard from the sages in כרם- Kerem in כרם ביבנה, Kerem
B'Yavne, right where the חכמים Chachamim gathered after the חורבן בית המקדש,
churban Beis Hamikdash, where the seat of rabbinic sort of authority was,
in יבנה, Yavne, it was called a vineyard because they were like
in rows of sages. כולם צריכן להמתין שלשה חדשים. Kulam tzrichin l'hamtin
shlosha chodashim. Everybody, all the women, no matter what the circumstance, all
need the three months wait, we don't make a distinction whether they
could have been- whether they could be pregnant whether, you know, whether
there was an opportunity for them to have sex or not to
have sex. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא, Amlei Reb Yirmiya l'Reb
Zeira, now we're not done with the objection. ירמיה Yirmiya said to
רבי זירא Reb Zeira כי עיילת לקמיה דרבי אבהו ki ayalta l'kamei
d'Reb Abbahu when you go in front of רבי אבהו, Reb Abbahu,
רמי ליה, rami lei, show him this following contradiction. מי אמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי, Mi amar Reb Yochanan halacha k'Reb Yosi, does
רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan really say we rule like רבי יוסי, Reb
Yosi, meaning the earlier version of רבי יוחנן, Reb Yochanan, that we
went like רבי יוסי Reb Yosi to say that it makes a
difference whether she could be- whether she could have been having sex
or not? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, V'amar Reb Yochanan, halacha
k'stam mishna, doesn't רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan say we rule like a
סתם משנה? stam mishna? ותנן Usnan and our משנה Mishna says, כל
הנשים לא ינשאו ולא יארסו עד שיהו להם שלשה חדשים, kol hanashim
lo yinasu v'lo yearsu ad sheyehu lahem shlosha chodashim, all women have
to wait three months, אחת בתולות ואחת בעולות, achas besulos v'achas beulos,
whether they have had sex or not. So anyway, so you see
so his question is, although before we already made the point of
saying that was a דעת יחיד, daas yachid, okay, that's just a
normal idea that why are you פסקן-ing pasken like a דעת יחיד
daas yachid against a רבים? rabbim? So we're saying, okay, that סתם
stam voice in the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, although it was
a סתם stam voice was really a דעת יחיד. daas yachid. Fine,
but even if it- in the- behind the scenes it's a דעת
יחיד, daas yachid, in the משנה Mishna it's presented as a סתם.
stam. And רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan says that we go like a
סתם. stam. So how could here he be going not like the
סתם? stam? אמר ליה Amlei he said to him, דרמי לך הא,
d'rama lach ha, the one who showed you
that- who like who- asked that question, לא חש לקמחיה, lo chash
l'kimchei,
is not concerned for his flour, you know, because learning תורה Torah
is often compared to like grinding, you know, wheat and flour, basically
he's not concerned for the type of question he asks. That's a
lousy question. סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת, Stam v'acharakav machlokes, that is not
a- a simple סתם משנה, stam mishna, that is a סתם משנה
stam mishna, followed by a מחלוקת, machlokes, because you have the סתם
stam voice and then it says that רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda disagreed.
So when רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan says we rule like a סתם
משנה, stam mishna. it's when the סתם stam is said in an
uncontested way and maybe different opinions will be found in other משניות
Mishnayos or in a ברייתא, Braisa, but in that very משנה Mishna,
the opposing voice is- is voiced right away. So that's not the
context that- now you're still right you have to ask a question
about יחיד ורבים, yachid v'rabbim, so we ident- so we identified
that that סתם stam behind the scenes really is a דעת יחיד.
daas yachid. But in terms of the principle that you go by
a סתם stam regardless of the יחיד ורבים yachid v'rabbim question, that's
a רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan principle, that's not true when embedded in
that סתם stam is the opposing voice. סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת, Stam
v'acharakav machlokes, אין הלכה כסתם, ein halacha k'stam, we don't rule like
the סתם, stam we don't necessarily rule like the סתם. stam דאמר
רב פפא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן, D'amar Rav Papa v'isima Reb Yochanan, because
רב פפא Rav Papa says and some say even רבי יוחנן Reb
Yochanan himself says, מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם הלכה כסתם. machlokes v'acharakav stam
halacha k'stam.
If you have a מחלוקת machlokes followed by a סתם משנה, Stam
Mishna then we go like the סתם משנה. stam Mishnah, סתם ואחר
כך מחלוקת, Stam v'acharakav machlokes,
if you have a סתם stam, and then the מחלוקת machlokes follows
it, אין הלכה כסתם, ein halacha k'stam, we don't go like the
סתם. stam. Again, not necessarily clear it means we דפקא dafka go
against the סתם, stam but certainly it means we're not obligated to
go like the סתם stam. in that case. Okay, now we're going
to analyze this a little bit and digress from our discussion to
talk about this issue about how- do we always say הלכה כסתם
halacha k'stam and how do you understand סתם ואחר כך מחלוקת. stam
v'acharakav machlokes. You- you should know these types of questions, by the
way, come up all the time in הלכה Halacha and like the-
you know, there's developed a whole hermeneutics around interpreting the שולחן ערוך.
Shulchan Aruch. Like if the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch has an opinion
and then he says ויש אומרים, v'yesh omrim, like da-da-da-da, ויש אומרים
דא. v'yesh omrim da. So, okay, which is the הלכה, halacha, the
first one or the ויש אומרים? v'yesh omrim? Let's say he says
ויש אומרים v'yesh omrim this and then he gives you the opinion.
So it's sort of like a similar question, like סתם ויש אומרים,
stam v'yesh omrim, ויש אומרים וסתם, yesh omrim v'stam, there's a whole
hermeneutics around the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch about how to interpret that.
סתם משנה stam Mishnah. is רבי מאיר Reb Meir in general, right?
Yeah, but and- and here was רבי מאיר Reb Meir as well.
So that's interesting, you're right, that the fact that the גמרא, Gemara,
you know, סתם משנה אליבא דרבי מאיר stam Mishna aliba d'Reb Meir
or is it like, you know, or is it- or does it
mean that it's like really just the opinion of רבי מאיר Reb
Meir as opposed to, you know, equal opinions by other- by you
know other- it's a good point that the גמרא Gemara before said
oh it's not a- it's not a רבים, rabbim, it's a רבי
מאיר, Reb Meir, that's what every סתם stam, generally is. All right,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, this is a סתם
ואחר כך מחלוקת. stam v'acharakav machlokes. So we don't have to rule
like the סתם, stam although we might in the end rule like
it because of this other משנה Mishna about- ברייתא Braisa about כרם
ביבנה. Kerem B'Yavne. Now we're going to have a discussion about
this. מסתמיך ואזיל רבי אבהו אכתפיה דרבי נחמן, Mistamech v'azil Reb Abbahu
akasfei d'Reb Nachman, so רבי אבהו Reb Abbahu was being supported and
being sort of carried on the shoulders of רבי נחמן, Reb Nachman,
שמעיה shemayeh his attendant. So אזיל רבי- azil Reb ומסתמך ואזיל רבי
אבהו
אכתפיה דרבי נחמן Mistamech ve-azil Rabbi Abahu achitfeih d'Rabbi Nachman שמעיה Shama'ei
ואזל רבי
אבהו va-azal Rabbi Abahu אילקט מיניה ilkat minei הלכות מיניה hilchos minei
and the attendant was sort of gathering up הלכות Halachas from רבי
אבהו. Rabbi Abahu. You know, figure like if you're already driving the
rabbi to the airport, you might as well שמועס schmooze with him
and learn some תורה Torah from him. So he was gathering הלכות
Halachas from him. בעי מיניה, Ba'ei minei, asked him, מחלוקת ואחר כך
סתם מהי? Machlokes ve-achar kach stam mai? What do we say in
the case where it's a מחלוקת machlokes and then a סתם? stam
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, הלכה כסתם, halacha k'stam,
so then we rule like the סתם. stam, Okay, סתם ואחר כך
מחלוקת מהי? Stam ve-achar kach machlokes mai? If the סתם stam? followed
by a מחלוקת, machlokes, what do you say? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
אין הלכה כסתם, ein halacha k'stam, we don't rule like the סתם.
stam. Again, I'm not sure if he means we don't rule or
we don't necessarily rule. Anyway, סתם במתניתין מחלוקת בברייתא. Stam be-matnisin machlokes
be-braisa. Let's say you have a סתם משנה, stam Mishnah. but in
a ברייתא braisa it's recorded as a debate. What do you say,
מהי? mai? אמר ליה, Amar lei, הלכה כסתם, halacha k'stam, we still
go back to סתם. stam You know, I mean, if it's almost
like a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, I mean, you know, even if
the debate is in the משנה Mishna if it comes later, we
go back to סתם. stam. So certainly if the debate is, you
know, located elsewhere and in the ברייתא, braisa, we'll go back to
סתם משנה. stam mishna Okay, what about this? מחלוקת במתניתין וסתם בברייתא.
Machlokes be-matnisin ve-stam be-braisa. There's a מחלוקת machlokes in the משנה Mishna
and a סתם stam. in the ברייתא. braisa. Now maybe that's better
than מחלוקת אחר סתם, machlokes achar stam, because at least in the
context of the ברייתא, braisa, it's uncontested. So maybe and since in
that source it's uncontested, maybe we should go like it. מהי? mai?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, וכי רבי לא שנאה
רבי חייא מנא ליה? V'chi Rabbi lo shna'ah Rabbi Chiya m'na lei?
If רבי Rabbi didn't teach it, didn't teach this
סתם, stam. means that he didn't necessarily buy into the fact that
this was the הלכה, halacha, where does רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya get
the idea that this is necessarily the הלכה? halacha? So, what, what
was this case?
I'm sorry, what?
Oh, I see.
We find such a case? No, he would say that why, why
should he rely on the authority of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya if
רבי, Rabbi, you know, basically saying the משנה Mishnah has ultimate authority.
So just because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya has decided to teach it
as a סתם, stam does not mean that, you know, why should
that have authority if רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, if רבי Rabbi apparently
chose not to teach it as a סתם stam, or not, you
know, not to voice that opinion. Okay, so anyway which all that
seems pretty obvious because again, you know, if even within the משנה,
Mishnah the only time you go by סתם stam, is when it's
first the סתם stam and then the מחלוקת, machlokes, it would seem
any other configuration of locating where the סתם stam is, you know,
whether you put it, you know, in a ברייתא, braisa, whether you
put it and so on, you obviously give it lesser weight.
Isn't it first the מחלוקת machlokes and then the סתם? stam I'm
sorry, in that same משנה Mishnah or could be let's say one
משנה?
Mishnah, Okay, so that תוספות Tosafos and רש"י Rashi is discuss exactly
where is the מחלוקת machlokes located in different מסכת, maseches, in the
same משנה, Mishnah later in the same מסכת, maseches, later in the
same סדר, seder, I'm not getting into that. Okay. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, והתנן. ve-hatnan. Okay, so now getting back to this issue that
we always go like a סתם. stam He's going to say, wait
a minute, I have a סתם stam? that I know we don't
פוסקין pasken like. Again, this is the whole thing with these כללים
klalim is that you never really always go by these כללים, klalim,
they're just like general rules. You know, even this, yeah, that's what
I just said is not. Anyway, so it says like this, right.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, והתנן, ve-hatnan, I'll show you a משנה Mishnah?
that we don't go like a סתם משנה. stam mishna? We taught,
מסרקה
של פשתן, masreika shel pishtan, you have a comb used for combing
flax, שניטלו שיניו, shenitlu shinav,
that the teeth of the comb have been
removed, ונשתיירו בו שתיים, ve-nishtayaru vo shtayim, and two of the teeth
are still present. So, you know, you can use to comb something
if the two teeth are next to one another. So in that
case טמאות, tmeios,
it is שניטלו שיניו ונשתיירו בו שתיים טמאות shenitlu shinav ve-nishtayaru vo
shtayim tmeios ואחת טהורה. ve-achas tehorah. If it's two then, then they're
טמאות. tmeios. If it is one, then it is טהורה tehorah because
what are you going to use a comb with that has one
tooth in it? Okay, so it's no longer a כלי kli receptive
to be able to מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. וכולן שניטלו אחת ואחת
בפני עצמן, ve-chulan shenitlu achas ve-achas bifnei atzman, however as far as
the comb is concerned, as far as the individual teeth that break
off individually, טמאות, tmeios, those are טמאות, tmeios, because you know you
could use a tooth of a comb as like a toothpick or
something like that. Okay, now של צמר, shel tzemer, if however it's
not a flax comb but a wool comb, שניטלו שיניו, shenitlu shinav,
that again its teeth were removed, אחת מבין שתיים טהורה. achas mibein
shtayim tehorah. If it's one between every two, so there's a gap
between the teeth, then it's טהורה. tehorah. Okay, you got the idea?
No two teeth are next to one another. נשתיירו בו ג' במקום
אחד, nishtayaru vo gimel bemakom echad, if there are three in one
place, טמאות, tmeios, then it's טמאות. tmeios. Now obviously that's funny because
if it said before that if there's a gap it's טהורה, tehorah,
it would suggest that even two together are טמאות. tmeios. So the
גמרא Gemara will get to that. הייתה חיצונית
אחת מהן, hayesa chitzonis achas meihen, if the outer teeth is one
of these three in one place, then טהורה, tehorah, then it is
טהורה tehorah because these outer teeth are not as functional as the
inner teeth or whatever רש"י Rashi has different explanations, we don't have
to worry about it. ניטלו
שתיים ועשאן למלקט, nitlu shtayim va-asaan le-malket, if two teeth were removed
and they were sort of combined by the bottom piece of the
comb, right, and they broke off and they're sort of held together,
then you could use it as a type of a tweezers. So
in that case, right, the two teeth like together like a type
of a toothpick or something, so in that case טמאות, tmeios, the
teeth themselves are טמאות. tmeios. אחת והתקינה לנר או למיתוח, achas ve-hikina
le-ner o le-misuach, if you have one and you fixed it and
you like, you know, like I don't know, whittled it or something
to use it to like clean as a lamp cleaner or to
stretch out the. thread, טמאה, tme'ah, that's טמא. tamei. Okay, that was
all fascinating. Why's that relevant for us? דקיימא לן דאין הלכה כזאת
המשנה. dekayma lan de'ein halakha k'zos hamishna. Oh, that's a סתם משנה
stam mishna and we know that we don't rule that way! Of
all the things to know we don't rule like, how relevant is
that Mishnah? Anyway, that was his question. How can you say we
go like a סתם משנה? stam mishna. Here's a סתם משנה stam
mishna we don't go like. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
him, בר מינה דהיא, bar minah dehi, put that case aside. רבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish de'amri tarveihu, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish both say זו אינה
משנה, zu einah mishna, we don't rule like that Mishnah. Okay, we'll
say what? That's an exception. We know we don't rule that way.
מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, but now the Gemara isn't done. Why not?
Let's give a reason why is it an exception. אמר רב הונא
בר מנוח משמיה דרב אידי בר בריה דרב איקא, Amar Rav Huna
bar Manoach mishmei de'Rav Idi bar brei de'Rav Ika, משום דקשיא רישא
לסיפא, mishum dekashya reisha l'seifa,
because the Mishnah itself is internally problematic.
The רישא reisha doesn't, the beginning doesn't agree with the end. דקתני,
Dekatani, the beginning says, של צמר, shel tzemer, excuse me, the end
says, של צמר שניטלו שיניו אחת מבין שתיים, shel tzemer shenitlu shinav
achas mibeyn shtayim, no, the second section, two parts of the second
section. The wool one, שניטלו שיניו אחת מבין שתיים טהור, shenitlu shinav
achas mibeyn shtayim tahor, if there's a gap between the teeth, it's
טהור. tahor. הנשאר בו שתיים במקום אחד, hanish'ar bo shtayim bemakom echad,
if two are right next to each other, no gap, then טמא,
tamei, it's טמא. tamei. והדר תני, V'hadar tani, by the way all
these things as טהור tahor and טמא tamei means susceptible for becoming
טמא tamei because it's still a כלי. kli. Okay, והדר תני, v'hadar
tani, and then the end of the end says, נשתיירו בו ג'
טמא, nishtayru bo gimel tamei, three together are טמא. tamei. ג' אין
שתיים לא, gimel in shtayim lo, only three, not two? So the
whole Mishnah is a problematic Mishnah. The Gemara says, ומאי קשיא, umai
kashya, why is it difficult? דילמא הא בגבייתא הא בברייתא, Dilma ha
b'gavyaysa ha b'varaysa,
maybe it's a difference between the outer teeth and the inner teeth.
Because the way Rashi basically says, it's like the outer teeth are
for really doing the, it's like, you know, it's like a
two-leveled comb, so the outer teeth are higher and the inner teeth
are lower, and the outer teeth are actually for like scraping the
stuff and removing it and then the inner teeth are for like
collecting the loose stuff that's freed up. Some, something like that. So
anyway, it makes a difference whether the outer teeth or the inner
teeth, the outer ones you need there to be three in one
place to be effective, the inner ones even two in one place.
אלא מהא, Ela meha, from here. דקתני ובכולן שניטלו אחת אחת בפני
עצמן טמאות, dekatani uv'khulan shenitlu achas achas bifnei atzman tme'os,
by the case of the flax, it says each individual tooth is
broken off individually is טמאות, tme'os, because you could like use it
as a toothpick or something. ואף על גב דלא תיקנה, v'af al
gav d'lo tiknah, and by the flax case, it doesn't say that
you have to do anything to fix it to make it usable
in that fashion. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the end by
the wool case. אחת ותיקנה לנר או למיתוח טמאה, achas v'tiknah l'ner
o l'mituach tme'ah, one of the teeth of the wool comb breaks
off and you did something to fix it to make it usable,
then it's טמאה. tme'ah. תיקנה אין לא תיקנה לא, tiknah in lo
tiknah lo, only if you fixed it? So you see it's a
contradiction. אמר אביי ומאי קשיא, Amar Abaye umai kashya, why is that
a contradiction? I mean, one's a flax comb, one's a wool comb.
דילמא הא בקתיה הא בלא קתיה, dilma ha b'kataya ha b'lo kataya,
maybe one is with the, you know, with the, the, the, the
sort of the piece on the bottom and one is, you know,
you know, you know how these things are attached to like, you
know, on a comb, right? There's a break off just the tooth
or does it break off with a little bit of the base.
Okay,
so oh my God, that's a very interesting comb. Okay, anyway, fine.
But if it breaks off with a little bit of the base,
then you can use it more easily, right? I mean, because then
you actually have like a little mini handle attached to it. So
maybe when you don't have to fix it is when it breaks
off, breaks off with the base, and when you do have to
fix it is when it breaks off without the base. אמר רב
פפא ומאי קשיא, Amar Rav Papa umai kashya, here's another way of
distinguishing. דילמא הא בקטינתא הא בעלימתא, dilma ha b'katinta ha b'alimta,
maybe one is a thin and also one was flax, one was
wool, maybe one was a thin tooth and one was a thick
tooth. So there's different ways that it was different, that's not a
problematic. אלא משום דמסיימי בה דוקנאיי, Ela mishum demasaymi bei dokanay, okay,
you know what, you're right. The Mishnah is not problematic at all.
But people that have, that, but the people that are precise about
the גירסא, girsa, about the text, when they finish teaching the whole
Mishnah, they have a few words at the end. And what are
the few words they have at the end? זו דברי רבי שמעון.
zu divrei Rabbi Shimon. Ha!
So it's not a סתם stam. משנה. Mishnah, You're right, we don't
rule like that way, but that's because although your version of it
is סתם, stam their other versions of it that aren't סתם. stam,
Okay, that was all a huge digression and quite bizarre of all
the cases to ask about not ruling like a סתם stam. משנה
Mishnah that we went over there.
There's five, six different cases that the Mishnah gave. I know. And
we don't rule like any of them?
Or I don't know, we don't have to rule like any of
them. I, I don't know. Okay, now we move back to this
issue of the three months wait. So we have this big question,
right? We have the question about do we always demand the three
months wait or do we say לא פלוג? lo plug? And that
was the whole issue. Do we rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who says we, we, we judge it case by case or do
we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says לא פלוג? lo
plug? And we said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan went back and forth
on that. So let's see how the Gemara ends up. שלח רבי
יצחק בר אבין, Shlach Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avin, רבי יצחק בר אבין
Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avin sent, מארסין תוך ג', ma'arsin toch gimel,
you could do אירוסין eirusin within three months. Okay, which is because
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that אירוסין eirusin is not a problem
because you're not putting yourself, the woman isn't putting herself in a
context where she can be having sex yet. וכן עושין מעשה, v'chein
osin ma'aseh, and that's how we would rule. וכן הורה רבי אלעזר
למלמדנו, v'chein hora Rabbi Elazar l'melamdeinu, and this is what רבי אלעזר...
Rabbi Elazar... משום ר' חנינא הגדול, mishum Rebbi Chanina hagadol, רובו של
ראשון, rubo shel rishon,
and we would also be taught the majority of the first month,
ורובו של שלישי, v'ruvo shel shelishi, and the majority of the third
month, ואמצעי v'emtza'i משלם, mishalem, and the entire middle month would be
enough. Now, that's bizarre and רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot don't discuss
it. I assume other ראשונים Rishonim did, I did not get a
chance to look. But like, if you really are in a situation
where you're demanding three months, what is this about most of one,
the second, and most of the third? That's not going to do
enough of a job of distinguishing between whose kid it is unless
he feels, he doesn't buy into what the גמרא Gemara said before,
you don't believe that a kid could be born after six months
and two days, maybe he felt you needed seven full months. If
you felt you needed seven full months, then two months and a
little bit really would be enough. It's not exactly clear what this
other opinion is, but anyway the גמרא Gemara is not focusing on
that. It's focusing on whether you have to wait three months, on
what situations you have to wait three months. Yes?
תוספות Tosafot says three months, so this is only for ארוסה. arusah.
So that was the other possibility, that when he says an ארוסה
arusah doesn't have to wait, he didn't mean you don't have to
wait at all, he meant you don't have to wait the full
three months, you can do this version of three months, and then
it's not as lenient of a פסק. psak. Okay, so that's possible.
It's possible that he's combining those two things. It's either two separate
teachings or a combined teaching. Okay,
fine, that's that.
Now אמימר Amemar שרי לארוסי ביום תשעין. shari l'arusi b'yom tishin. Now
that actually would fit a little bit because now what we're seeing
is leniencies,
but not much leniencies. Like okay, maybe אירוסין, erusin, not like we
don't demand three months at all, we'll be a little bit more
lenient in how we define the three months. So אמימר Amemar said,
you know what? If it's just אירוסין erusin and not נישואין, nissuin,
you can get married on day ninety. You don't have to wait
till day ninety-one. Okay, so alright, thank you. אמר ליה רב אשי,
amar lei Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to אמימר,
Amemar, והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו v'ha Rav u'Shmuel d'amri taveihu צריכה
להמתין ג' חדשים, tzricha l'hamtin gimmel chodashim, you have to wait three
months, חוץ מיום שמת בו chutz mi'yom she'meis bo וחוץ מיום שנתארסה
בו, v'chutz mi'yom she'nis'arsah bo,
not including the day of death, you start counting the ninety days
after the day of death, and not including the day that you're
doing the אירוסין. erusin. It had, the אירוסין erusin has to be
on day ninety-one. So first of all, they're already talking explicitly אירוסין,
erusin, even אירוסין erusin needs three months, right? Even though he's not
yet in a context of having sex. And not even a leniency
in counting the ninety days, it has to be on day ninety-one.
So he said no, ההוא לענין מינקת איתמר. hahu l'inyan meynekes itmar.
That was said not about the ninety days, that was said about
the waiting before remarrying a woman who is nursing. Remember we discussed
that as well. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו Rav u'Shmuel d'amri taveihu צריכה
להמתין כ"ד חודש tzricha l'hamtin kaf daled chodesh חוץ מיום שנולד בו
וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו. chutz mi'yom she'nolad bo v'chutz mi'yom she'nis'arsah bo.
The waiting before of a woman who's nursing, it was assumed nursing
would take place for the first two years. So they said you
would have to wait twenty-four months, not including the day of that
the baby was
born, starting the day after the baby was born, and that the
actual day of the אירוסין erusin is day after the twenty-four months.
So he said you got the version wrong, it wasn't three months,
it was twenty-four months, it was taught about something else. So right
now we are saying a basic לא פלוג, lo pelog, and at
most what we're debating is like can you have a somewhat creative
way of defining the three months in that case? Maybe that was
the first opinion that you just make it like the majority of
three months or maybe that's this idea of at least counting day
ninety and not ninety-one. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says וההוא דעבד סעודת
אירוסין ביום תשעין. v'hahu d'avad seudat erusin b'yom tishin.
There's a guy again, all this is אירוסין. erusin. So the end
of the סוגיא, sugya, although in the גמרא Gemara we said רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan first said we go, we don't say לא פלוג,
lo pelog, and אירוסין erusin you wouldn't need it. Here consistently, you
always are going the end of the discussion is even by אירוסין
erusin you always need three months. And most of the discussion is
what do you do about day ninety? So the גמרא Gemara says
wasn't there a guy that made a סעודת אירוסין seudat erusin on
day ninety ואפסדיה רבא לסעודתיה, v'afseidei Rava l'seudateih, and רבא Rava basically
made him, you know, made him throw out the whole wedding feast.
Said no, I'm sorry, you're not getting married today, you have to
wait till tomorrow to get married. So the גמרא Gemara says ההוא
סעודת נישואין הוה. hahu seudat nissuin havah. No,
you got the case wrong. That wasn't a סעודת אירוסין, seudat erusin,
that was a סעודת נישואין. seudat nissuin. נישואין nissuin we would obviously
wait till day ninety-one. והילכתא, v'hilchata, and the הלכה halacha is צריכה
להמתין כ"ד חודש, tzricha l'hamtin kaf daled chodesh,
when you're waiting twenty-four months, it has to be a full twenty-four
months, so that's by the case of מינקת, meynekes, חוץ מיום שנולד
בו וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו, chutz mi'yom she'nolad bo v'chutz mi'yom she'nis'arsah
bo,
and not including the day that the baby was born and not
including the day of the wedding, of the קידושין. kiddushin. וצריכה להמתין
ג' חדשים, u'tzricha l'hamtin gimmel chodashim,
and when you're waiting three months for getting remarried this woman after
husband dies or divorces her, חוץ מיום שמת בו chutz mi'yom she'meis
bo וחוץ מיום שנתארסה בו, v'chutz mi'yom she'nis'arsah bo, not including the
day of death
and not including the day of אירוסין. erusin. So more than the
question of day ninety and ninety-one, what's most significant about the conclusion
is that we say the לא פלוג, lo pelog, that you have
to wait three months even in a case of אירוסין. erusin. Now
this again, one might come to the conclusion that Michael suggested yesterday,
which is if we're saying לא פלוג, lo pelog, then maybe you
can't use a pregnancy test. Maybe לא פלוג, lo pelog, we say
you always need three months, doesn't matter this version, that version, etc.
But since the גמרא Gemara before did discuss tests, so I say,
well, why not have her walk? Why not do this? Why not
do that? One could say no, לא פלוג, lo pelog, that in
all circumstances you need to determine whether or not she's pregnant, but
when that determination have to be three months, if we have a
definite way of determining it through some other means, like a modern
pregnancy test, that might be fine even if, so it would be
a little bit funny. You would say, okay, here's a woman, she's
a virgin, she's underage, or whatever, she's post-menopausal let's say. That's the
case. Once post-menopause,
we say לא פלוג, lo plug, so therefore take a pregnancy test
and then we'll be okay, right? But that's like, but that is
there are two separate questions. One is do we demand some way
of determining, and then is that way of determining is it only
three months or in theory if we could find another means we
would be happy with that other means. And it makes a certain
amount of sense, because saying לא פלוג lo plug is not saying
like we really believe that this post-menopause woman might be pregnant. Saying
לא פלוג lo plug is we don't want to start distinguishing the
cases because there will be some cases that we would really need
to determine it then you know and then by making distinction some
of those cases will slip through the cracks. So we're going to
demand it in all cases. Fine, we'll demand in all cases, but
what are we going to demand? Let's demand a pregnancy test. We
don't necessarily demand three months. It's a מחלוקת הפוסקים machlokes haposkim whether
you can use pregnancy tests here.
No, I mean, let's say that you would, would
you make the woman take it? Yeah, according to that logic you
would. You would even a post, even an older woman you would
have her do a pregnancy test and then you'd be done. Yeah.
So there's the case of יבום. yibum. Someone, you know, had a
kid, right? Yeah. And then how long is she available for a
kid? Is it a month or is it a year?
I'm sorry, what?
Is it a month or is it a year?
Is what a month or a year?
Available for a kid because of a child?
No, it's a month. It's only available for is for more than
a year's for a parent.
Then how come it's חוץ מן האלמנה? chutz min ha'almana? Let's say
she loses a kid she doesn't have to wait a month for.
Well, no, no, no, that's first of all. האלמנה Ha'almana from her
husband. We're going to get to the אבילות. aveilus. But then married,
had a kid...
What did he say? He lost the kid.
Oh, you meant the case about the miscarriage. Well,
no, what kid are you talking about? It's just a case that
her husband died.
The only exception
is potentially מפני האבל. mipnei ha'eivel. Right.
So all
right, so there could be other cases that people are sitting שבעה
shiva for a parent or whatever, but that's not intrinsic to the
case. Okay, so that's exactly what we turn to now is the
position of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi that if this is a, although
he says although if he's only doing אירוסין, eirusin, רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi says you can get married right away. Again, because now this
new set, this new reality of אירוסין eirusin doesn't entitle, is not
yet in the context of sex. So אירוסין eirusin he said you
could do right away. He says that's not in a case when
a woman just lost her husband, her husband died, then you cannot
do it within the first month because then she is still in
אבילות. aveilus. The problem that the גמרא Gemara is going to have
is that we normally assume that there's no אבילות aveilus for husband
and wife until after the נישואין, nisuin, not at the stage of
אירוסין. eirusin. So what is רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi talking about in
terms of אבילות? aveilus? Okay, that now you could say okay maybe
that's when she was נשואה nesua before. All right, so she's נשואה,
nesua, right? Meaning there's two stages, right? The point here is remarrying,
sorry I'm just using this diagram real fast from before. But anyway,
right here she is, right here's רחל Rachel married to ראובן. Reuven.
Okay, he died. They were נשואין. nesuin. So she has to sit
שבעה shiva for him, she's in אבילות aveilus for a month. Okay?
And now but she's only going to do אירוסין eirusin with שמעון.
Shimon. So since she's only doing אירוסין eirusin with שמעון, Shimon, she
can do that right away because there's no, because they're not having
kids right away. אירוסין eirusin right you don't have the possibility of
having kids until נישואין. nisuin. So you can do this right away,
you don't have to wait three months. But in the first month
she's still sitting שבעה, shiva, she's still in אבילות aveilus for ראובן.
Reuven. Now if she was only ארוסה arusa to ראובן, Reuven, it
wouldn't be a problem basically because there's no אבילות aveilus for a
relationship that was just an אירוסין eirusin relationship. But she was נשואה
nesua to ראובן, Reuven, he died, she's in אבילות aveilus for a
month, so even though this אירוסין eirusin can happen right away because
they're not yet having sex, but nevertheless, you have to wait at
least a month so that she's no longer in אבילות. aveilus. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. חוץ מן האלמנה. Chutz
min ha'almana. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
he says I don't get it, I don't get
it why this makes sense. I'll tell you a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. מה במקום שאסור לכבס מותר לארס. Ma bimakom she'asur lachabes mutar
le'ares. He says I don't think that אירוסין eirusin itself should be
a problem when a person is during the month of אבילות, aveilus,
or even during the שבעה, shiva, right? Because remember the שמחה simcha
comes, primary שמחה simcha comes through נישואין. nisuin. And you might know
the הלכה halacha by the way that you can actually do קידושין
kiddushin as opposed to נישואין nisuin even on like תשעה באב Tisha
B'av itself because the גמרא Gemara says שמואל Shmuel says שמא יקדמנה
אחר, shema yekadmena acher, right, somebody else will beat you to it.
So anyway, so this woman is being so anyway so now we're
saying look since we're talking only about אירוסין eirusin here because otherwise
it would be a problem of waiting three months, why is this
a problem during אבילות? aveilus? Since when is אירוסין eirusin a problem
during אבילות? aveilus? It's not talking about נישואין. nisuin. So קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, מה במקום שאסור לכבס מותר לארס, ma bimakom she'asur lachabes
mutar le'ares, a place where
you're not allowed to do laundry because of אבילות aveilus issues, you're
still allowed to do
אירוסין. eirusin. מקום Makom שמותר לכבס shemutar lachabes during the month, right,
you're only not allowed to do laundry. during the first week, during
the rest of the month where you're allowed to do laundry in
אבילות, avelus, אינו דין שמותר לארס, eino din she'mutar l'ares, how much
more so should אירוסין erusin be allowed? מאי היא, mai hi, now
where what is this case where you can do you cannot do
laundry but you can do קידושין? kiddushin? תנן, tenan, we taught: שבוע
שחל תשעה באב להיות בתוכה, shavua she'chal tisha b'av l'hiyot b'tocha,
the week of Tisha B'Av, שבוע שחל בו תשעה באב, shavua she'chal
bo tisha b'av, אסור לספר ולכבס, assur l'saper u'l'chabes, you can't get
a haircut and do laundry. ובחמישי מותר מפני כבוד שבת, u'v'chamishi mutar
mipnei kavod shabbos, on Thursday you can for Shabbos purposes, so that's
bracketed. ותניא, v'tanya, we taught in a Baraita: קודם הזמן הזה, kodem
hazman hazeh, before this before this time, presumably meaning before Tisha B'Av,
העם ממעטין בעסק, במשא ומתן, ובבניין, ובנטיעה, ha'am m'matin b'esek, b'masa u'matan,
u'v'vinyan, u'v'netiya,
you don't do business and building and so on. ומארסין, u'ma'arsin, but
you can still do קידושין. kiddushin. אבל לא כונסין, aval lo konsin,
but you can't bring the woman in, you can't do נישואין. nissuin.
ואין עושין סעודת אירוסין, v'ein osin se'udat erusin, but you can't do
an אירוסין-like erusin feast, but you can still do the act of
קידושין. kiddushin. So you see, ואירוסין, v'erusin, yeah, that's קידושין. kiddushin. So
you
see, that's presumably שבוע שחל, shavua she'chal, but you can do קידושין
kiddushin even though you can't do laundry. How much more so during
the rest of the month where you're allowed to do laundry you
should be able to do קידושין. kiddushin. So the Gemara says: לא,
כי תניא היא קודם דקודם. lo, ki tanya hi kodem d'kodem. No,
no, no, when that says "before this time" it doesn't mean שבוע
שחל, shavua she'chal, it means before the שבוע שחל shavua she'chal you're
allowed to do kiddushin, but during the שבוע שחל shavua she'chal you're
not allowed to do kiddushin. אמר רבא, amar rava, וקודם דקודם נמי
קל וחומר. v'kodem d'kodem nami kal v'chomer.
So what? I'll make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer during before the
שבוע שחל. shavua she'chal. ומה במקום שאסור לישא וליתן, u'mah bimkom she'assur
l'issa v'litein,
remember you're not allowed to do business right, משנכנס אב ממעטין בשמחה.
mishenichnas av m'matin b'simcha. So the whole the whole nine days you're
not allowed to do business, ומותר לארס, u'mutar l'ares, but you can
still do קידושין. kiddushin. מקום שמותר לישא וליתן, makom she'mutar l'issa v'litein,
when you're allowed to do business, like during the rest of the
month of, and we're switching back from Tisha B'Av period to personal
personal אבילות, avelus, when you're allowed to do business during the rest
of the month of אבילות, avelus, not during the first week, אינו
דין שמותר לארס, eino din she'mutar l'ares, how much more so should
קידושין kiddushin be allowed during the first month of אבילות? avelus? So
the Gemara says: לא תימא דרבי יוסי אומר כל הנשים יתארסו, lo
teima d'rabbi yose omer kol hanashim ye'arsu, fine. So the first answer
is, I'm just going to tell you the answer at the end
because it's going to be a little frustrating in the middle before
we get there. The answer at the end is going to be
you can't compare Tisha B'Av הלכות halachos to personal אבילות. avelus. In
Tisha B'Av הלכות halachos it's not as personal, so therefore we will
allow קידושין kiddushin under certain circumstances. Personal אבילות avelus is much more,
you know, highly specific to the person himself, we're not going to
allow קידושין. kiddushin. That's going to be the answer at the end.
But at this stage the Gemara, in order to make it work,
how is it that Tisha B'Av we allow it and how is
it and how is it that Rabbi Yose has got a problem,
we're going to completely switch the גירסא girsa of Rabbi Yose and
say that what Rabbi Yose is saying is a problem here is
not אירוסין, erusin, אירוסין erusin is not a problem and what Rabbi
Yose is actually saying a problem here is נישואין. nissuin. And we're
going to go through a whole עמוד amud now of switching the
גירסא girsa of Rabbi Yose, yes, very quickly.
And regarding the business, most people I know work normally during the
nine days except for Tisha B'Av.
Yeah, so there's a question of what type of לישא וליתן l'issa
v'litein we're talking about, you know, whether it's לישא וליתן של שמחה
l'issa v'litein shel simcha etc., we'll worry about it when we do
תענית. taanit.
Yeah, but you know, although if this issue isn't for any other
reason, then there'd still be a similar concern.
Yeah, but just that this is intrinsic to the day. לא תימא
דרבי יוסי אומר כל הנשים יתארסו, lo teima d'rabbi yose omer kol
hanashim ye'arsu, fine. I can see the point. אירוסין erusin should be
allowed during the month of אבילות. avelus. So Rabbi Yose is not
having a problem with saying,
with talking about whether women can do אירוסין erusin or not, and
say that she's an אבילה aveila she can't do אירוסין. erusin. אלא
אימא כל הנשים יינשאו. ela eima kol hanashim yinashu.
What he's saying is like this, he's saying not he's saying all
women can do נישואין, nissuin, except for a woman who's an אלמנה
almanah because that's during the month of אבילות. avelus. So you're right,
he's talking about נישואין, nissuin, he's not talking about אירוסין. erusin. אירוסין
erusin would be okay. Gemara says: one minute, so נישואין nissuin is
only a problem for the אלמנה? almanah? Isn't נישואין nissuin a problem
for all the women? Right, we're talking about נישואין nissuin now, we've
switched the terms of the game. ולית ליה לרבי יוסי להבחנה, v'leit
lei l'rabbi yose l'havchana, isn't Rabbi Yose concerned about distinguishing whose child
it is? The Gemara says: לית ליה, leit lei, yes, he's not
concerned. Okay, which is a great answer, what basis of the Gemara,
oh my god, so yeah, he was not concerned about that, I
don't know exactly why not. איבעית אימא לעולם אית ליה, ibayis eima
l'olam it lei, fine, he is concerned about whose child it is.
ואימא רבי יוסי אומר כל ארוסות גרושות יינשאו. v'eima rabbi yose omer
kol arusot gerushot yinashu. What he's saying is like this, he's saying
not he's saying
all women who are ארוסות arusot can go ahead and, well let
me just check the Rashi for a second, what's with
an ארוסה? arusa?
Right, right, right, meaning, meaning he's reversing the order. Right, he is
saying, right remember if you don't say לא פלוג, lo plug, then
if one of these stages of אירוסין erusin you don't have to
worry because there's no sex. It's only a problem if there's sex
at both ends. So instead of saying all
נשואות nesuot can do אירוסין, erusin, except for during she's an אלמנה
almanah because then she's in in אבילות, avelus, now we're saying there's
no that wouldn't prevent אירוסין. erusin. So we're going to switch the
terms. Not anything, we're going to say here she's an ארוסה, arusa,
so that's why it's not a לא פלוג. lo plug. That’s why
there’s no concern of whose child it is and here she’s undergoing
נישואין, nissuin, right? So we switched it. As opposed to this being
a נשואה neshuah and this being ארוסה, arusah, and that’s because this
is an ארוסה arusah there’s no concern of whose child it is,
but if it’s only אירוסין eirusin there’s no אבילות aveilus concern. Okay,
flip it. This is the ארוסה, arusah, so there’s no concern of
whose child it is. This is the נישואין, nissuin, and now she’s,
women are normally allowed to do נישואין nissuin if they started as
an ארוסה arusah because there’s no concern of whose child it is,
but they’re not allowed to do it if they’re in the first
month of אבילות. aveilus. That’s why it says כל הגרושות, kol hagrushot,
if she’s a divorcee, if she’s an ארוסה arusah who is a
divorcee, ינשאו, yinase'u, then she can do נישואין. nissuin. But if she’s
an ארוסה arusah who is an אלמנה, almanah, then she’s in אבילות
aveilus and then she cannot. מן האירוסין? min haeirusin?
An אלמנה almanah from the אירוסין eirusin then.
Yeah, well, that’s what the גמרא’s Gemara going to ask after that.
Okay, but okay, so then let’s say because now right, that’s going
to now put that question, right? אי הכי היינו רבי יהודה. ee
hachi hainu Rabbi Yehuda.
So that’s רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
so again, it’s not exactly clear why it asks if that’s רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just says anyway you can
do either as long as either end is אירוסין eirusin you don’t
have to wait. הגמרא HaGemara says no, איכא בינייהו נשואה לאירוסין. ika
beinaiahu neshuah le-eirusin. No,
the difference is is when a woman starts off as a נשואה,
neshuah, can she do אירוסין? eirusin? רבי יהודה סבר נשואה מותרת לאירוסין,
Rabbi Yehuda savar neshuah muteres le-eirusin, רבי יוסי סבר נשואה אסורה לאירוסין.
Rabbi Yossi savar neshuah asurah le-eirusin.
So basically he’s only allowing
an ארוסה arusah to do נישואין nissuin and then talking about whether
or not there’s a marriage concern, whereas what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows either an ארוסה arusah to
do נישואין nissuin or a נשואה neshuah could do
אירוסין. eirusin. Okay? So רבי יהודה סבר נשואה Rabbi Yehuda savar neshuah
can do אירוסין, eirusin, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is only talking
about, it said, it would maybe assume that a נשואה neshuah could
not do אירוסין eirusin and he’s only talking about an ארוסה arusah
doing נישואין. nissuin. Have I completely confused you? But the basic point
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn’t care as long as one of
those stages is אירוסין. eirusin. What we are saying now is that
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is focusing in on this scenario, that the
first stage is אירוסין eirusin and the second stage is נישואין. nissuin.
That he says is allowed except that in case of אלמנה almanah
she has to wait for the month. Now the גמרא Gemara says
וסבר רבי יוסי נשואה אסורה לאירוסין? ve-savar Rabbi Yossi neshuah asurah le-eirusin?
Does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi say that a נשואה neshuah cannot do
אירוסין? eirusin? Meaning, again, it’s not exactly clear what moves the גמרא
Gemara to say this, because the גמרא Gemara until this point, the
whole debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
had really just been whether there’s a concern about אבילות aveilus or
not, that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi introduces the idea of אבילות. aveilus.
For some reason now that the גמרא’s Gemara switching the parameters and
I can’t really explain to you why, it’s assuming that if רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi is talking about this case about an ארוסה arusah
doing נישואין, nissuin, that that would mean that in order to make
him different from רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he would reject the case
of a נשואה neshuah doing אירוסין eirusin and saying a נשואה neshuah
doing אירוסין eirusin would not be allowed under any circumstance. It's not
exactly clear why the גמרא’s Gemara assuming that but that’s what it
is, and now it’s questioning that assumption. וסבר רבי יוסי נשואה אסורה
לאירוסין? ve-savar Rabbi Yossi neshuah asurah le-eirusin? Would רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
say a נשואה neshuah can’t do אירוסין? eirusin? והתניא רבי יוסי אומר
כל הנשים יתארסו חוץ מאלמנה מן האיבול. ve-hatanya Rabbi Yossi omer kol
hanashim yit-arsu chutz m'almanah min ha-eibol.
All women could do אירוסין eirusin except for an אלמנה almanah because
of the אבילות. aveilut. Anyway by the way that’s back to what
the משנה Mishnah is saying, right? All women except for an אלמנה
almanah doing אירוסין. eirusin. We’re back to the woman who was a
נשואה neshuah now doing אירוסין. eirusin. וכמה איבול שלה שלשים יום, ve-kama
eibol shelah shloshim yom, and for thirty days. וכולן לא ינשאו, ve-kulan
lo yinase'u,
and that’s about an אלמנה almanah doing אירוסין, eirusin, but all women,
presumably all ארוסות arusot shall
not... excuse me,
all women even נשואות neshuot can’t do נישואין nissuin עד שיהיה להם
ג’ חדשים. ad sheyihiye lahem gimel chodashim. So again the simple sense
of this ברייתא Braita is what the משנה Mishnah says, that אירוסין
eirusin is okay except for אבילות aveilus purposes, but נישואין nissuin is
no good. The גמרא Gemara says האי מאי קושיא? hai mai kushya?
Why is that difficult? אילימא דקתני רבי יוסי אומר כל הנשים יתארסו,
eileima de-katani Rabbi Yossi omer kol hanashim yit-arsu,
all women can have אירוסין, eirusin, and that you assume that that
means that all נשואות neshuot can have אירוסין eirusin and which is
exactly what he said in the משנה. Mishnah. So מי אלימי ממשנתינו?
mi alimei mi-mishnateinu? How’s that stronger than our משנה? Mishnah? The same
way we completely changed the version of our משנה, Mishnah, we’ll change
the version of the ברייתא. Braita. אוקמינא
בארוסות. okminah b'arusot. By the משנה Mishnah we said we’re not talking
about נשואות neshuot doing אירוסין, eirusin, we said we’re talking about the
opposite: ארוסות גרושות דינשאו. arusot grushot de-yinase'u. והכי נמי כל ארוסות גרושות
ינשאו. ve-hachi nami kol arusot grushot yinase'u. We’ll completely reverse the text
of the ברייתא. Braita. Both the משנה Mishnah and the ברייתא Braita
has רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying a נשואה neshuah can do אירוסין
eirusin and we reversed it to say an ארוסה arusah can do
נישואין. nissuin.
אלא מסיפא ela mi-seifa דקתני וכולן לא ינשאו עד שיהיה להם ג’
חדשים. de-katani ve-kulan lo yinase'u ad sheyihiye lahem gimel chodashim. Okay, so
this is about a נשואה neshuah and a נשואה neshuah cannot do
נישואין. nissuin. הא ארוסה שפיר דמי. ha arusah shapir dami.
presumably a נשואה *nesua* could do אירוסין erusin *eirusin* and you're telling
me that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbi Yehuda* would say that a
נשואה *nesua* could never do אירוסין erusin *eirusin*. So אמר רבא תרצה
ואימא הכי *amar Rava tartzei v'eima hachi* fine, we might as well
reread the end of the ברייתא braita, *braisa* also. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi אומר כל ארוסות גרושות ינשאו *Rebbi Yose omer kol arusos grushos
yinasehu* and an ארוסה *arusa* who's a גרושה grushah *grusha* not an
אלמנה almanah. *almanah* can do נישואין nissuin, *nisuin*, חוץ מן האלמנה מפני
האיבול *chutz min ha'almanah mipnei ha'eibol* except for אלמנה *almanah* because of
the אבלות *aveilus* וכמה איבול שלו שלשים יום *v'kamah eibol shelo sheloshim
yom* and that's for thirty days. So that's about a woman who's
an ארוסה *arusa*, an ארוסה *arusa* can do נישואין nissuin *nisuin* unless
she's an אלמנה *almanah*. Now in the reverse case, ונשואות *u'nesuos* if
she starts off as a נשואה *nesua* לא יתארסו עד שיהיו להם
שלשה חדשים *lo yisarsu ad she'yehu lahem shalosh chodeshim* have to wait
three months. ואלמנה מן האירוסין *v'almanah min ha'eirusin* fine. So anyway, that
was very, very complicated and that's completely rewriting all the text. Yeah,
and what's really not even unclear is why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
assumes that just because we flipped this case for רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi *Rebbi Yose*, why he would have to hold that a נשואה
*nesua* is always a problem? Why can't he hold like רבי יהודה
*Rebbi Yehuda* holds, as long as one of the ends is אירוסין
erusin. *eirusin*, you're okay. All right, whatever. The basic thing that you've
got to know is that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is bothered
with why should אירוסין erusin. *eirusin* be a problem during אבלות *aveilus*?
And what it has answered is that we're going to flip the
case and say it starts as ארוסה *arusa*, that's why there's no
need of three months and it's נישואין nissuin, *nisuin* that's problematic for
אבלות *aveilus*. But now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to ask, so
forget all that whole rewrite, that's not so relevant. What the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara*'s going to ask though is if you flip the case,
why is there אבלות *aveilus* for a husband who died who you
were just an ארוסה *arusa* to? Okay, so either way it's a
question. If the ארוסה *arusa* is at the new end, that should
not create be a problem to get married during אבלות *aveilus*, to
do קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* as opposed to נישואין *nisuin*. And if the
ארוסה *arusa* is at this end, it's well why is there אבלות
*aveilus* in the first place? Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, ואלמנה מן האירוסין מי אית לה איבול *v'almanah min ha'eirusin
mi is lah eibol*? Does somebody who's a widow from אירוסין erusin,
*eirusin* have אבלות *aveilus*? והתני רבי חייא בר אמי אשתו ארוסה *v'hatani
Rebbi Chiya bar Ami ishto arusa* if a man's wife who is
just an ארוסה *arusa* to him, not yet נשואה *nesua*, so they
don't yet have a lived relationship, it's just contractual at this point.
לא אונן *lo onen* he is not an אונן *onen* for her
if she dies, ולא מיטמא לה *v'lo mitama lah* if he's a
כהן kohein, *kohen* he doesn't become טמא *tamei* to her, וכן היא
לא אוננת ולא מיטמאה לו *v'chein hi lo onenes v'lo mitama'ah lo*
if he dies, she's not an אוננת *onen* and she doesn't become
טמאה *tamei* to him although obviously there's not a הלכה halacha *halacha*
about her as a prohibition of כהונה *kehunah* but it means she
does not have to busy herself with his burial obligations. מתה *meisah*
when she dies, אינו יורשה *eino yorshah* he does not inherit her.
מת *meis* if he dies, גובה כתובתה *govah kesuvah* she would never
anyway inherit her husband even if they were נשואות *nesuos* but so
what she does but here interestingly she is at least entitled to
a כתובה ketubah *kesuvah* even though it's only אירוסין erusin? *eirusin*, this
is in a place where the כתובה ketubah, *kesuvah* obligation not the
ongoing כתובה ketubah, *kesuvah* obligations but the basic two hundred זוז zuz,
*zuz* would be promised from the time of the אירוסין erusin. *eirusin*.
אלא *ella* anyway you see that there's no אבלות *aveilus*. Okay, so
we basically are back to where we started. Nobody debates that there's
no אבלות *aveilus* in this everybody agrees that there's no אבלות *aveilus*
if it was just an ארוסה *arusa* relationship. So you would not
have to wait. This has to be a נשואה *nesua*. And if
that's a נשואה *nesua*, then this in order so that it's no
need for a three
months' wait, it goes back to אירוסין *eirusin*. If this is back
to אירוסין *eirusin*, why is אירוסין *eirusin* a problem during the אבלות
*aveilus* period? And now we finally get back to the original question
with all skipping over their whole complicated rewrite in the middle. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says אלא תנאי היא *ella tanai hi*. This issue
of אירוסין *eirusin* during אבלות *aveilus* is a debate of תנאים *tannaim*.
You showed that it wasn't a problem during the תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av. *Tisha B'Av* period, it's really a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. דתניא
*d'tanya* we saw in a ברייתא braita *braisa* מראש חודש ועד התענית
*merosh chodesh v'ad hata'anis* from ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* until the fast,
the nine days, ממעטין בעסקיהם מלישא ומליתן *mema'atin be'iskeihem milisa u'militein* you
limit the amount of business you do, מלבנות ולנטוע מלמיארס ומלישא *milivnos
v'linto'a melime'aras u'milisa* from doing building and planting and from אירוסין *eirusin*
and נישואין *nisuin*. So this says even during the nine days you
don't do אירוסין *eirusin*. שבת שחל תשעה באב Tisha B'Av, להיות בתוכה
*shabbos she'chal Tisha B'Av lihyos besochah* and the שבוע שחל בו תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av *shavua she'chal bo Tisha B'Av* אסור לספר ולכבס *assur
lesaper u'lechabes* you can't even get a haircut and do your laundry.
ויש אומרים כל החודש אסור *v'yeish omrim kol hachodesh assur* and some
say that even the whole nine days you don't get a haircut
and do laundry. Okay, so there's an opinion that says אירוסין *eirusin*
is a problem during אבלות *aveilus* and that's who רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi *Rebbi Yose* is going like. That explains by the way why
he's arguing with רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* because maybe only רבי יוסי
*Rebbi Yose* says it's a problem to אירוסין *eirusin* during the אבלות
*aveilus*. So מתקיף לה רב אשי *matkif lah Rav Ashi* רב אשי
*Rav Ashi* asks ממאי דליארס אירוס ממש *mimai d'le'eiras eirus mamash*? How
do you know in that ברייתא braita *braisa* by תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av *Tisha B'Av* it was talking about literally just the act of
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*? דילמא למיעבד סעודת אירוסין seudat erusin. הוא דאסור *dilma
leme'evad seudas eirusin hu d'assur*. Maybe it means only doing a wedding
feast for the act of אירוסין *eirusin*. אבל לארוס שפיר דמי *aval
l'eiras shapir dami*. But the act of אירוסין *eirusin* maybe it's okay
and we're back to square one.
So maybe it's okay to do just the act of קידושין kiddushin,
*kiddushin*. Back to square one. אי הכי מלישא ומלינשא *ei hachi milisa
u'milinesah* if that's true then you would say when it says you
can't do נישואין *nisuin* למינשא נמי *le'inesah nami*. When they have a
סעודת נישואין הוא דאסור, הא לישא שפיר דמי, ha lissa shapir dami,
would you say the same thing that when it says you can't
do נישואין, it only means you can't do a wedding feast? Or
the actual wedding you can do? So the Gemara, and we know
that's not true, so the Gemara says: הכי השתא, hachi hashta, that's
not a comparison. בשלמא נישואין בלא סעודה איכא שמחה, bishlama nissuin belo
seuda ika simcha,
I understand נישואין without the feast is still שמחה, simcha, they start
living together, it's a real marriage. אלא אירוסין בלא סעודה מי איכא
שמחה? ella erusin belo seuda mi ika simcha? But אירוסין by itself,
there is no שמחה. simcha. So meaning I'm committed to the idea
that אירוסין is not a problem during אבילות. aveilus. And therefore, I'm
going to even if you have a ברייתא, first of all all
the evidence shows that it's not a problem אירוסין. Even if you
show me a ברייתא that says it is a problem, I'm going
to choose to interpret it as סעודת אירוסין. So we're back to
square one. What's רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yossi's problem? Because I see you
can do קידושין kiddushin. during the nine days, as we know the
הלכה halacha, is you can even do קידושין kiddushin. during תשעה באב.
Tisha B'Av So what's רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yossi's problem? So the גמרא
says, well then אלא אמר רב אשי, ella amar Rav Ashi, שני
אבילות חדשה מאבילות ישנה. shani aveilus chadasha m'aveilus yeshana. No, there's a
difference between a new אבילות aveilus and an old one. Old one,
תשעה באב, which is like a commemorative אבילות aveilus that we're supposed
to get into that experience, but it's not really fresh, so the
demands are not as weighty, as opposed to the demands of a
fresh אבילות. aveilus. ושני אבילות דרבים מאבילות דיחיד. v'shani aveilus d'rabbim m'aveilus
d'yachid. Now this could go both ways. You could say a communal
אבילות aveilus is more weighty, right? It's something that affects the entire
people. But also, it's less personal, as opposed to a personal אבילות,
aveilus, that's more personal. So you know what? You might be right,
might be even on תשעה באב you could do קידושין, but at
least what רבי יוסי is saying, maybe רבי יהודה disagrees, but whatever
evidence you bring from תשעה באב is not relevant. And רבי יוסי
is at least entitled to say that in a personal, new אבילות,
aveilus, there should be an איסור issur of קידושין. So we're back
to the simple read of the משנה. Mishnah. Yes, it's just אירוסין.
Maybe it's not a problem during the תשעה באב period, but רבי
יוסי is saying it is a problem during the personal אבילות aveilus
period. Yes, Dov, you had a question?
It's corroborated something I thought, I don't know if it's הלכה, but
someone in אבילות, aveilus, they say: I'll go to the wedding just
for the חופה, chuppah, but not for the סעודה seuda with the
music. Right, itself as a מעשה. ma'aseh. Right, it always seemed to
me you shouldn't go at all, unless you're going to be מקפיד.
makpid.
Yeah, so that's true, I mean, so there are different issues that
we're talking about during י"ב חודש לאביו ולאמו, yud-bet chodesh l'aviv u'l'imo,
and now we're talking about other cases where you're a relative and
that not going would be a real, a real issue for the
חתן וכלה. chassan v'kallah. I mean, whatever, there's a lot of distinctions,
you know, but yes.
I wanted to ask a question though of the I know that
we don't, our ספק safek is not כהלכה k'halacha in terms of
אירוסין, but does any פוסקים poskim deal with the issue of propriety
of getting engaged if let's say your fiancee dies or something like
that during that time? Or does no one care?
No, there are issues about that. The גמרא talks about it about,
you know, even בית הקברות, beit hakevarot, somebody basically approached,
you know, there's a case in the גמרא about
a man whose wife had just
died approached I think his
wife's sister or the wife's whatever. Anyway, but the basic point was
that that was done also because of a feeling like needed to
marry somebody because he had to provide for the household. Yeah, so
there is a discussion there around the propriety issues. Hananya, did you
have a question?
Now also with our, with our...
I don't know, I mean there's always propriety issues, yes.
But we're just talking about הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus here, we're not
talking about the three months or the one month.
Well that's the point, within a context of waiting three months or
whatever, you're saying wait, wait, you forgot about the fact that if
her husband died, there's an אבילות aveilus issue to discuss. That's all
he's saying, but that's taking it from some different area, right, yeah.
Is the כתובה beginning at אירוסין?
Is the כתובה, the ongoing obligations of the כתובה, the ones that
are sort of during the reciprocal obligations during marriage, only is during
נישואין, not during קידושין. The only question is, does the base amount,
the 200 זוז, that's like the lump sum payment in the case
of divorce or death etc. to protect her,
to provide for her, that might already be at the time of
אירוסין. That's what this ברייתא assumes, okay. But
it's not given till then, then you basically, clothing and food and
domicile etc., yeah. Okay, so let's just, we're actually ahead, not ahead,
we're up, caught up. Let's get to the next דף, daf, we'll
be ahead for once. We'll read the משנה. Mishnah. ארבעה אחים נשואים
ארבע נשים ומתו.
arba'ah achim nesuim
arba nashim u'metu. No, no, it's not going to be as complicated
as you think, okay.
Four brothers are married to four women, notice it doesn't even say
they're sisters. I know. It basically just wants to give you a
scenario where one brother is confronted with multiple יבום yibbum opportunities from
multiple brothers, okay. So ומתו, u'metu, all these four brothers die, and
now there's another fifth brother around. אם רצה הגדול שבהם לייבם את
כולן הרשות בידו. im ratza hagadol shebahem l'yavem et kullan hareshut b'yado.
So we've already said that the responsibility devolves around the oldest brother.
If now there are four women that are from four different brothers
waiting for יבום, yibbum, he can choose to do יבום yibbum with
all of them, right? And they, you know, so it doesn't say
no, you do one, now the other brothers have their primary responsibility
with the other. מי שהיה נשוי לשתי נשים ומת. mi shehaya nasui
l'shtei nashim u'met. מי שהיה נשוי לשתי נשים ומת, Mi she-hayah nasui
l'shtei nashim u-meit, somebody was married to two women and he died,
ועשה חליצה של אחת מהן פוטר צרתה. ve-asah chalitzah shel achat me-hen
poter tzartah. This we've known from the beginning, right? The act of
sex with one of them or the act of חליצה chalitzah with
one gets all the others off the hook.
ביאה Biah or חליצה chalitzah is done with one and the others
automatically are now, you know, free. היתה אחת כשרה ואחת פסולה. Haytah
achat k'sheirah ve-achat p'sulah. Let's say of the two wives, one of
them was already פסולה לכהונה, p'sulah l'kehunah, one was already a גרושה
grushah, from a previous marriage. Okay, אם היה חולץ, im hayah choleitz,
חולץ לפסולה. choleitz l'psulah. If you're going to do חליצה, chalitzah, might
as well do חליצה chalitzah with the one who's already a גרושה,
so you don't make her פסולה psulah to a כהן, okay? Because
the other one is just an אלמנה. ואם היה מיבם, ve-im hayah
meyabem, if you're going to do יבום, yibum, מיבם לכשרה. meyabem l'k'sheirah.
You should do יבום yibum with a כשרה. k'sheirah. Now that's not
clear, does it mean you should even with the כשרה, k'sheirah, only
with the כשרה? k'sheirah? Fine. We will see in the גמרא, but
we can now say that we are actually a little bit ahead.